A Guide to the Union Tank Car Company Records FA083
Rockefeller Archive Center
Union Tank Car Company records
1889-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Union Tank Car (Firm)
Standard Oil Company
FA083
8.46 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access
The archival material has been reformatted. Access to the original paper records is restricted. Microfilm user copies are available for research. The microfilm does not include the Photographs or two oil portraits (which are available at the discretion of RAC).
Arrangement note
The Union Tank Car Company Records are organized into four series:
Series 1 - Alphabetical File
Series 2 - Shop Records
Series 3 - Financial and Administrative Records
Series 1045 - Photographs
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The archival material has been reformatted. Access to the original archival material is restricted. User copies of the microfilm are available for scholarly access. The microfilm does not include the Photographs or two oil portraits.
Biographical/Historical note
The Union Tank Car Company (hereafter UTCC) originated in the Star Tank Line founded in 1866 by J. J. Vandergrift. Vandergrift, one of the early competitors of the Standard Oil Company, organized this Line to handle oil freight between the Pennsylvania oil fields and Chicago. After Vandergrift's holdings were sold to Standard Oil in 1873, the Star Tank Line became that company's carrier. The name was changed to Union Tank Car Company in 1878.
As part of the reorganization of the Standard Oil Trust in 1890-1891, the Union Tank Line was incorporated under the laws of the state of New Jersey on August 1, 1891. Standard Oil of New Jersey was its holding company. The Union Tank Line remained exclusively a carrier of Standard Oil products until the dissolution of the Trust in 1911.
Greater diversification of customers and services developed during the 1920s and 1930s. This was signaled as well by the change of name to UTCC and the relocation of the company's offices to Chicago in 1927. After 1931, the UTCC branched into chemical hauling and tank car manufacturing. In 1957, the UTCC acquired the Graver and Phoenix Manufacturing Companies, the first in a series of corporate mergers which was to make the UTCC one of the largest tank carrier companies in the world. In 1969, the UTCC created a holding company, Trans Union Corporation, and the latter company, together with its subsidiaries (including UTCC), was acquired in 1981 by The Marmon Group, owned by the Pritzler Family of Chicago.
Presidents of the Union Tank Line/Tank Car Company during this period were as follows: Wesley H. Tilford (1891-1905); Henry E. Felton (1905-1919); William A. Barstow (1919-1922); E. C. Sicardi (1923-1926); Lauren J. Drake (1927-1947); B. Clifford Graves (1947-1955); Edwin A. Locke, Jr. (1955-1962); Jerome W. Van Gorkom (1962-1975).
Scope and Contents note
The Union Tank Car Company records date from 1889-1978. The records as received by the Rockefeller Archive Center are incomplete. The records, which include correspondence, memoranda, clippings, pamphlets, reports, financial and legal materials, and blueprints, only partially document the company's activities.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 3B 18
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Union Tank Car Company Records were donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center by the Trans Union Corporation in August 1981.
Separated Materials
The collection also includes two oil portraits of UTCC presidents Wesley H. Tilford and Henry E. Felton.
United States; Business
- Alphabetical File, 1889-1978; 1; 2 document cases
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject (e.g. Acquisitions, Financial Statements) or document type (e.g. By-Laws, Certificate of Incorporation).
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, pamphlets, clippings, financial and legal materials.
  - Acquisitions, Dispositions, Liquidations, 1959-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel M 1, Frame 1)
  - Balances (Trial), 1891, 1908-1909, 1911, 1913-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel M 1, Frame 2)
  - Brunswick-Union (Proposed Plan of Combination), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel M 1, Frame 3)
  - By-Laws, 1914-1926, 1951-1969, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel M 1, Frame 4)
  - Certificate of Payment of Capital Stock, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel M 1, Frame 5)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1891-1930 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel M 1, Frame 6)
  - Certificate of Incorporation - New Jersey, 1889-1900, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel M 1, Frame 7)
  - Company History, 1957, 1960, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel M 1, Frame 8)
  - Contract - Tank Cars (Standard Oil-Union Tank Line), 1912 (Reel M 1, Frame 9, Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial Settlements, 1902-1905 (Reel M 1, Frame 10, Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Listing Agreement - New York Stock Exchange, 1921-1930, 1953, 1956-1958 (Reel M 1, Reel 11, Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Listing Agreement - New York Stock Exchange, 1959, 1961, 1967-1971, 1973, 1975-1976 (Reel M 1, Reel 12, Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Listing Agreement - New York Stock Exchange, 1977-1978 (Reel M 1, Frame 13, Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mayor of Streator, 1963-1964 (Reel M 2, Frame 1, Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Phoenix Manufacturing Company, ca. 1958, 1962 (Reel M 2, Frame 2, Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Resolutions (Secretary's Records), 1912-1922, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel M 2, Frame 3)
  - Securities Exchange Act Registration, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 17, Reel M 2, Frame 4)
  - Smith and Loveless, Inc., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 18, Reel M 2, Frame 5)
  - Stockholders Meetings, 1892-1926 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel M 2, Frame 6)
  - "Union Tank Line News" - Souvenir Number, August 1919 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel M 2, Frame 7)
  - Miscellany - Historical, 1902-1929, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 21, Reel M 2, Frame 8)
  - Miscellany, 1958-1975, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22, Reel M 2, Frame 9)
- Shop Records, 1912-1955; 2; 3 document cases
  This series is arranged alphabetically by site.
  Series 2 contains correspondence referring to service agreements, followed by correspondence, memoranda, leases and reports related to UTCC repair shops throughout the United States. The bulk of this material concerns leasing arrangements and contracts with customers--mostly Standard Oil affiliates. This series also contains blueprints.
  - Canceled Car Service Agreements (A-Ci), 1947-1955 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel M 2, Frame 10)
  - Canceled Car Service Agreements (Co-G), 1947-1955 (Reel M 2, Frame 11, Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Canceled Car Service Agreements (H-P), 1947-1955 (Box 3, Folder 25, Reel M 2, Frame 12)
  - Canceled Car Service Agreements (Q-W), 1947-1955 (Box 3, Folder 26, Reel M 2, Frame 13)
  - Albany, New York, 1926, 1934, 1942, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 27, Reel M 2, Frame 14)
  - Bay City, Michigan, 1921-1924, 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 28, Reel M 2, Frame 15)
  - Baytown, Texas, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 29, Reel M 2, Frame 16)
  - Blissville, New York, 1918, 1928, 1931 (Reel M 2, Frame 17, Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Bo-Br (Reel M 2, Frame 18, Box 3, Folder 31)
    Boynton, Oklahoma, 1931 Bristow, Okalahoma, 1931-1933
  - Buffalo, New York, 1912, 1918-1925, 1936 (Reel M 2, Frame 19, Box 3, Folder 32)
  - E-Fo (Reel M 2, Frame 20, Box 3, Folder 33)
    East Boston, Massachusetts, 1915, 1926-1939 Fort Worth, Texas, 1931-1932, 1936
  - Franklin, Pennsylvania, 1915-1928, 1931, 1936-1938 (Reel M 3, Frame 1, Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Franklin Park, Illinois, 1933 (Reel M 3, Frame 2, Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Greybull, Wyoming, 1919, 1924-1925, 1938, 1943-1945 (Reel M 3, Frame 3, Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Jacksonville, Florida, 1915-1928, 1937, 1942, 1945 (Reel M 3, Frame 4, Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Laramie, Wyoming, 1920, 1925, 1931 (Reel M 3, Frame 5, Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Lima, Ohio, 1914-1925, 1932-1933, 1938 (Reel M 3, Frame 6, Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Louisville, Kentucky, 1918-1933, 1942-1945 (Reel M 3, Frame 7, Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Muskegon, Michigan, 1921, 1926, 1939 (Reel M 3, Frame 8, Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Muskogee, Oklahoma, 1933, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 42, Reel M 3, Frame 9)
  - Oil City, Pennsylvania, 1930-1931, 1937-1938, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 43, Reel M 3, Frame 10)
  - Okmulgee, Oklahoma, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 44, Reel M 3, Frame 11)
  - Parkersburg, West Virginia, 1917, 1920, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 45, Reel M 3, Frame 12)
  - Paulsboro, New Jersey, 1921-1922, 1927, 1932-1938 (Reel M 3, Frame 13, Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1912-1914, 1924, 1927, 1932 (Reel M 3, Frame 14, Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Port Tampa, Florida, 1916, 1919-1924, 1926-1927, 1931, 1934 (Reel M 3, Frame 15, Box 5, Folder 48)
  - River Rouge, Michigan, 1912, 1915, 1917-1918, 1920, 1922, 1927, 1930-1931, 1933, 1936, 1942, 1945 (Reel M 3, Frame 16, Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Salt Lake City, Utah, 1923, 1926-1927, 1943, 1945 (Reel M 3, Frame 17, Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Shreveport, Louisiana, 1927, 1929, 1931-1934, 1936 (Reel M 3, Frame 18, Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Wi (Reel M 3, Frame 19, Box 5, Folder 52)
    Wichita, Kansas, 1932, 1936-1938 Wilmington, North Carolina, 1923, 1942-1943
  - Wilson Point, Connecticut, 1922, 1926-1927, 1929 (Reel M 3, Frame 20, Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Winnett, Montana, 1922-1924 (Reel M 3, Frame 21, Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Blueprint - Baytown, Texas, 1928 (Box F 1, Folder 1, Reel M 3, Frame 22)
  - Blueprint - Blissville, Texas, n.d. (Reel M 3, Frame 23, Box F 1, Folder 2)
  - Blueprint - Buffalo, New York, 1903 (Box F 1, Folder 3, Reel M 3, Frame 24)
  - Blueprint - East Boston, Massachusetts, 1927 (Box F 1, Folder 4, Reel M 3, Frame 25)
  - Blueprint - Franklin, Pennsylvania, 1915, 1919, 1928 (Box F 1, Folder 5, Reel M 3, Frame 26)
  - Blueprint - Jacksonville, Florida, 1915, 1921, 1923, 1927 (Box F 1, Folder 6, Reel M 3, Frame 27)
  - Blueprint - Joliet, Illinois, ca. 1960 (Box F 1, Folder 7, Reel M 3, Frame 28)
  - Blueprint - Lima, Ohio, 1921 (rev. 1922), 1926 (Box F 1, Folder 8, Reel M 3, Frame 29)
  - Blueprint - Louisville, Kentucky, 1922, ca. 1933 (Box F 1, Folder 9, Reel M 3, Frame 30)
  - Blueprint - Muskegon, Michigan, 1921 (Box F 1, Folder 10, Reel M 3, Frame 31)
  - Blueprint - Muskogee, Oklahoma, 1933 (Box F 1, Folder 11, Reel M 3, Frame 32)
  - Blueprint - Parkersburg, West Virginia, 1917 (Reel M 3, Frame 33, Box F 1, Folder 12)
  - Blueprint - Phoenix Manufacturing Company Building, ca. 1960 (Reel M 3, Frame 34, Box F 1, Folder 13)
  - Blueprint - Port Tampa, Florida, 1919, 1926 (Reel M 3, Frame 35, Box F 1, Folder 14)
  - Blueprint - River Rouge, Michigan, 1923 (rev. 1930) (Reel M 3, Frame 36, Box F 1, Folder 15)
  - Blueprint - Wilson Point, Connecticut, 1915 (Reel M 3, Frame 37, Box F 1, Folder 16)
- Financial and Administrative Records, 1891-1930; 3; 10 document cases
  Series 3 contains claims ledgers, cash journals, general ledgers, and minute books.
  - Annuity Balance Sheets, ca. 1950 (Box 6, Folder 55, Reel M 4, Frame 1)
  - Balance Sheets (Trial and Final), 1891-1900 (Box 6, Folder 56, Reel M 4, Frame 2)
  - Claim Ledger No. 1 with Index, 1891-1914 (Box 7, Folder 57, Reel M 4, Frame 3)
  - Journal No. 2, 1895-1909 (Reel M 5, Frame 1, Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Journal No. 3, 1909-1927 (Reel M 5, Frame 2, Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Ledger "A" with Index, 1891-1905 (Reel M 6, Frame 1, Box 10, Folder 60)
  - Ledger "B" with Index, 1906-1914 (Reel M 6, Frame 2, Box 11, Folder 61)
  - Ledger "C", 1915-1920 (Reel M 7, Frame 1, Box 12, Folder 62)
  - Ledger "D", 1921-1930 (Reel M 7, Frame 2, Box 13, Folder 63)
  - Minute Books No. 1, 1891-February 1913 (Reel M 8, Frame 1, Box 14, Folder 64)
  - Minute Books No. 2, March 1913-April 1917 (Reel M 8, Frame 2, Box 14, Folder 65)
  - Minute Books No. 3, April 1917-1922 (Reel M 8, Frame 3, Box 14, Folder 66)
  - Minute Books No. 4, 1923-1926 (Box 14, Folder 67, Reel M 8, Frame 4)
- Union Tank Car Company photographs, 1960; 1045
  Union Tank Car Company
  - Union Tank Car Company, 1960 (Box 22, Folder 277)